Welcome everyone to sixth lecture for
CS3 to9A. Uh we'll today cover train
time scaling or scaling RL. So far we
have gone through several topics related
to test time scaling u feedback using uh
tools and code and then also robust
verification. Today we will see how we
can close the loop to improve the models
even further.
Okay. So today's lecture we will
actually cover three papers. Uh the
first paper will cover how can you uh
boost the reasoning capabilities of the
models with um putting rationals in um
problems. Uh this paper was is called
star. It was actually done by an author
at uh Stanford. The second paper we will
cover is deepseek math which talks about
mathematical reasoning and how that can
be uh boosted in u language models. And
then the third paper is more focused on
reinforcement learning and how when you
have to do uh reasoning with longer
reasoning chains how can you stabilize
that kind of reinforcement learning
algorithms.
So to
ground a lot of the to motivate a lot of
the uh papers that we'll present today
if you look at a benchmark called Amy.
So AM is a benchmark which is uh on
mathematical problems which uh tests for
mathematical reasoning. It's very
similar to say um it's it's more uh
complex mathematical reasoning problems
than say what was in a math benchmarks.
Uh we used math benchmarks earlier this
year and then that one is already
saturated and and not and contaminated
in most of the models. Basically most of
the models have been trained on it. So
we had to change the benchmark. So this
is uh Amy 2024 and AME 2025. The
benchmark that you use in homework one
um is a recent a recent benchmark that
is uh has mathematical reasoning
problems. And if you were to evaluate
GPD 3.5 which is 175 billion parameter
model you would get or or that's what
it's believed to be you get almost 5%
accuracy. But if you were to take
deepsek math which was uh using train
time scaling with on a 7B model it gets
51.7% accuracy and
with additional tricks it's able to even
get 60% accuracy and if you apply uh the
third paper that I will talk about
called Dapo uh on the quen 32B model you
are able to get 50% accuracy. So in the
prior work or in the first lecture we
were saying that as we scale the number
of parameters in the model that's when
the model capabilities go up the model
accuracy on benchmarks go up. But what
we are seeing in this particular slide
is that you can achieve a pretty high
performance on reasoning benchmarks with
smaller models. So how did these smaller
models uh get really performant? How did
they get really high accuracy? So that's
something that we will kind of explore
in this particular lecture. And the some
of the tricks that are being used uh to
achieve uh this are called train time
scaling. Um so typically if you try to
do reinforcement learning on reasoning
it will not work well and a lot of the
times the reason it doesn't work well is
uh because the implementation details
are hard to get right. So the the key
insights that we uh that we will study
today are that if you have a model
earlier you were just training it on
internet. So pre-training the technique
of model training was training the model
on internet. If you allow the model to
learn from their own outputs uh by
filtering cleverly you can improve the
models even further. Hence the class is
called self-improving AI agents algorith
uh class. Um and then the the amount of
compute you invest in training the model
on its own outputs can substitute for
the model parameters. This also
parallels some of the earlier efforts
where the amount of compute uh used in
training smaller models u if you could
increase the amount of data has been
shown to like help improve certain
benchmarks. And then the third point is
that when you're doing reinforcement
learning as opposed to supervised
learning, you have to really be careful
about uh details of the implementation
because as you scale up those
algorithms, uh the small fixes can be
extremely important. So the three
paradigms that I'm talking about here
are pre-training which is basically
you're training the model on internet um
that we have talked about in the first
lecture and we're not covering that much
in detail. And then the next technique
would be that fine-tuning which is how
you get your chatbots where you're
basically perhaps fine-tuning or doing
reinforcement learning with human
feedback or RLif on uh preference data
uh from humans and then the test time
scaling which was some of the techniques
that were covered uh in previous
lectures. Those are more techniques
where you're basically doing some sort
of say majority voting or inference time
sampling and then combining the outputs
from the uh how you sample from the
model. Um for example in homework one uh
you are evaluating majority voting then
you are evaluating some other techniques
that u combine and evaluate the errors
in what the model is producing and then
using that to improve the model. So test
time scaling is mostly inferencebased
techniques. Now if you take what the
model output filter after applying this
test time scaling and then use that to
fine-tune further that that's roughly
what train time scaling is. So if you
take nothing away from this entire
lecture but you just remember this loop
then you kind of have learned the basics
of what train time scaling does.
Questions?
How do you um know like when what is
like the good balance to distribute your
compute into train time scaling versus
test time scaling like
>> is there like a flat flat like ROI curve
that you reach at certain point after
investing in train time I mean great
question um let's hold that question
until the third paper
>> cool [clears throat]
uh but definitely ask that question
again
um so roughly um what happened last year
was that um what uh the reasoning model
this is a graph on 01 and 01's accuracy
on Amy uh on the it's passet one
accuracy on the y-axis and then the
amount of compute on x-axis and train
time is shown on the x-axis on left
graph and test time compute is shown on
the x-axis on the right hand plot. So
what is happening here is that as we are
increasing the test time compute that we
have already seen the passet one
aggressive should go up. So we this is a
log linear plot and so more inference
time compute better passet one accuracy
but what they're also showing is that if
you can increase the train time compute
then you can also improve passet one
accuracy. So what Owen showed uh for Amy
benchmark was that by increasing both
the train time compute and the test time
compute you are able to in improve the
accuracy on the benchmark and um so it
allows you for basically a circular loop
where like you can generate model
outputs and then feed them back to
improve the model on this particular
benchmark. Now why does this work? So
math is a domain in which there is
verifiability. So we had an whole
lecture on robust verification. So you
have the ability to know which outputs
are correct and which ones are not
correct. So you have some ability to
actually choose the correct outputs that
that can then feed into train time
scaling. So this works better in domains
where there is verifiability.
So uh typically why doesing um start to
help? Uh so this is a repeat of some of
the slides but I think it's very
important to remind folks that all the
reasoning models in Osiris or or Gemini
Gemini flash thinking or like valance in
other uh frontier labs the basically
reasoning allows us to solve for
difficult problems because when you're
solving a difficult problem you will not
just spit out the output even in chain
of thought and math problems when you
were asking the model to think step by
step it allowed certain amount of tokens
to be dedicated to um uh spelling out
the reasoning and step-by-step process.
So, thinking models use a chain of
thought where when they're attempting to
solve the problem and what these tokens
might get dedicated to is you will see
patterns like problem analysis where
they might actually try to understand
what the problem is describing. Task
decomposition. I'll show you an example
of this but that will where they try to
decompose the task into subtasks. Um
self-evaluation they might actually try
to look at the answer and then be like
okay this is not looking correct. Uh so
they might actually choose to uh
backtrack and uh recognize their own
mistakes and then backtrack to a
previous step where they redo the
problem and um they might uh try some
kind of different approaches. So it's
like a somewhat parallel search where
they might actually try multiple
approaches at the same time instead of
if the current one is not leading to a
solution. So it needs to have some sense
of whether it's the correct solution or
not. So here are some examples from um
actually um earlier version of the model
uh in 01 series. Uh so here the user is
requesting a bash script uh where it
wants to understand uh so it's
requesting a bash script that will
represent a string with the for with
this format and print out the transpose
in the same format. So it's taking a
matrix and printing the transpose and uh
what you see in the output is that the
model first tries to understand what the
user uh is asking in terms of input and
output formats before it tries to solve
the problem. So that's more of a problem
analysis kind of pattern. Another
example for the same problem you see is
that it tries to decompose the problem.
So it will actually once it understood
the problem it's saying that the
approach should involve maybe I should
parse the input string then build the
matrix transpose the matrix and then
output the matrix in the same format. So
it's breaking it into multiple steps.
While for this particular problem this
might be an overkill but in more complex
problems this might be a better way to
solve the problem because you've
decomposed the problem into smaller
steps. And then selfcorrection. So this
is a different problem from chemistry
where it's asking pH of uh some solution
on a chemical and um the model starts to
compute uh the pH value but then it um
suddenly has this notion of weight the
correct formula is different. So it
basically goes and changes the formula
that it was going to use. So even though
it's pulling from the knowledge that the
model already has it's actually um
correcting itself. So it has the
capability of selfcorrection.
And how does this help the model? So as
I was trying to explain before in
domains where you have verification like
computer programming or um data analysis
or mathematical calculation the win rate
over GPD40 which which was not a
thinking model you'll see that it's
greater than 50%. So uh certain domains
benefit way more from uh the strain time
scaling kind of techniques as opposed to
if you look at personal writing or
editing editing text there's not as much
improvement in terms of win rate. Win
rate means like if you were to give
humans output from GPD40 versus thinking
models um personal writing and editing
text may not see as much gains but
domains which have the ability to uh
verify and close the loop see more
gains.
um questions.
>> Mhm.
So the train time
to zero times it seems like performance
is better than the train performance
like on the right
but on the left side that is low. So in
this case it has performance actually
better than performance.
>> So in this particular plot it does look
like that. Um
>> but
>> there is no intuition around these
things as to like one should be better
than the other. I think I mean you have
to it this is one instantiation of where
things were and I just wanted to show
you the curve.
>> Performance is better than performance.
>> Mhm.
>> Just mean some suspicious
>> something suspicious going on. Okay.
>> I I copy the plot so some their graphs
are not always right as you might know
from their latest release.
>> Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> U okay so let's go back to the
fundamentals right so what is it that
we're trying to answer I think the
fundamental question we're trying to
answer is that in test time compute you
can basically if you go back to this
plot test time compute is very cheap for
someone to put uh because you've trained
a model and then you can go and do
multiple inferences and if one of the
answers is correct and you have a good
verifier on your end then you can
basically scale compute infinitely in
fact I think next Friday uh I'll go
through some papers including alpha code
for example and what you'll find there
is that if you can basically make make
your search infinite in some ways then
in test time you basically have a
solution that will be correct because
from test time scaling we do know that
there is a correct solution if you
repeatedly sample right um pain time
scaling the challenge will be that you
have to scale it correctly which we'll
cover in this lecture and then the
second bit is that there's a certain
amount of this closed feed feedback loop
has to have enough successes for the
train time scaling to work well.
So you will see that in the papers that
I'll present now. So that plot is
actually different the traditional
machine learning will compare between
the performance and test performance
because that clause is showing it's
actually more efficient if you boost the
computer to the test because when
computer increases the accuracy faster
like given the same computer to test
essentially you have better
>> so uh so there is a caveat to what
you're saying uh test time compute works
well in benchmark marks where the
verifiability is robust.
Okay.
>> Um otherwise you do need to get the
model to start to reason better because
you and and you need some verification
loops. So both serve their uh I mean
this is something we'll discuss in the
lecture but both serve their goals. So
like if you prefetch what I'll present
by the end of the lecture. uh when you
look at a pre-trained model what it is
good at is it has certain level of
capability in say solving mathematical
problems and solving reasoning problems
and reasoning about um finance or legal
or whatever based on whatever domains it
has seen already data in but then uh in
inference time you're basically getting
it to reason over multiple of these
traces and then picking one if you know
and have a good way to verify the
solutions then you can like pick one of
the solutions that's like saying I'm
going to throw spaghetti at the wall and
I know which where it should land. Um
otherwise with train time scaling you
can teach the model and boost the pass
at one accuracy so that uh there's more
likelihood that will emit the correct
output but you still need verification
of the loop.
More questions?
>> Yes. So, so when you're um fine-tuning
the model to be able to solve difficult
problems better, um does it
[clears throat] have any regression on
solving simpler problems? And if so, how
do you get that?
>> That one also needs to be let's let's
keep those questions. I like all the
reason all the questions, but we need to
get to the first paper and then we can
ask that one.
Typically there shouldn't be a
regression on solving um uh difficult uh
easy problems if you're solving
difficult problems unless you basically
go into like reasoning chains that are
completely um broken in some ways. So
repetitive reasoning chains
that which is called as overthinking.
So uh so let's cover the first paper
first where we are basically teaching
the model how to reason. Um so we are
boosting the reasoning capability of the
model with reasoning chains.
So let's take a uh let's take a look at
um how we can do that. So we already
covered this earlier and uh we showed
this in the first lecture. So chain of
thought in uh large language models
provides both interpretability and if
you ask the model to show its uh work
step by step then provides boosts
mathematical reasoning and we saw
several benchmarks common sense
reasoning and so on. So we want to
basically get the model to have strong
step-by-step reasoning capabilities u
along solving any problem. Uh what is
what is challenging with existing
approaches if you were to like try to
get this in existing approaches. So no
internet scale data has really reasoning
steps. Most of the time there are very
few internet sources that have the large
scale reasoning steps. And then if you
try to manually annotate reasoning steps
that's very expensive because you
literally need humans to annotate those
reasoning steps. And if you try to
automate this process of like generating
reasoning on based on known solution
patterns then that also uh works only in
very very specific domains. Uh and then
if you try to few short prompt, few
short prompting means like if you give
it a few examples of like here's a
problem, here is a reasoning chain, here
is an answer, then that still
underperforms uh models that can be
fine-tuned on just larger data sets. So
basically um small amount of uh
reasoning examples don't quite cut it
and you can just have a larger data set
without reasoning chains. So the the key
insight that star has is a very is very
simple. first thing. So this is a very
simple example like it will start with a
small number of of examples that is
reasoning [snorts] steps. It will
generate solutions. So say 10k problems.
Uh 10k is a representative number and
then it will only keep the ones that
have correct answers. Uh but it will
generate these uh problems with rational
and it can fine-tune on those and it can
repeat. So it can repeat this loop. So
this what's new here compared to what we
were doing in test time scaling is it's
only keeping the ones that have correct
answers. Now why did it not produce
correct answers on the other ones and
what can we do with those particular set
of examples? So that's the other
interesting bit. So in certain problems
where it could not solve the problem the
model got stuck. So what we want to do
is we basically
if we just fine-tune on the correct
examples the model is not able to learn
new how to solve new problems. Let me
cover this slide and then we can come
back. U so there's basically no no
signal. So what we do is we give the
model the answer and ask it to explain
backwards. So it's almost like I have
this question. I asked the model to
produce the answer but now the model did
not produce the correct answer. So I
give the model the answer and then I ask
you to produce the rational. So for
example the answer is 42. The human says
and then the model generates the
reasoning and then you can fine-tune the
model on again the problem rational and
the answer but don't show it the hint um
as if it was solved directly. So this
helps you expand the training set to
include more difficult problems now. So
uh basically it allows you to bootstrap
the reasoning capabilities u and not
just say limit it to u easy problems
that the model could solve earlier but
like now you can bootstrap iteratively.
So you basically generate reasoning
attempts you learn from successful
reasoning paths where the quality of the
reasoning paths is entirely based on uh
things being correct. And for failed uh
attempts uh you're basically
rationalizing them by saying okay here
is a hint uh please generate the
rationale and then you're using these
generated rationals as the training
data. So that's basically the algorithm
that they use in star. It's a very bare
bones and like you you can almost call
it an off policy reinforcement learning
technique. It's a very bare bones way of
producing uh reasoning techniques in a
model.
And the assumption that is being made in
this particular case is that how do you
know something is a good rationale?
They're assuming that if the model
output is correct, which in math uh they
found that that was generally true, the
correctness of the final output is a
proxy for the reasoning quality. And so
they're filtering incorrect answers.
Basically, they're assuming that um that
will be filtering out lower quality
reasoning chains, but there might be
scenarios where they um they're not
learning from incorrect reasoning chains
as a result.
and but they get higher quality training
data. And then the second bit is that
they assume that the uh language model
can generate valid reasoning paths when
it's given the answer as a hint. So it
kind of assumes that if I show show the
model the answer and then ask it to show
its work, it will be able to do so. And
then finally um there's some amount of
assumption that the initial language
model is strong enough to uh bootstrap
from few short examples. So if the class
of problems is way outside the
capability of the initial language model
then it will not make much progress on
this and this is where the iterative
aspect starts to become important. I was
seeing a couple of hands. So let's take
them one by one.
>> Um yeah I was just wondering so do they
start with like a math data set that has
like the correct answer and just doesn't
have reasoning right like that's how
they know what the correct answer is.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Cuz I was like how do they know
the correct answer? Yeah, everyone is
starting with a benchmark basically.
Yes.
>> Is there filtering that happens for step
three? Uh like are we worried that we
give like the correct solution and then
there's like issues in the reasoning
just to like get to the solution?
>> So they actually don't filter in step
three but there are follow on papers
that do filter in step three. Uh I mean
you can do some sort of process reward
model on top of the reasoning chains and
then say which of the steps make sense
or which of the steps don't make sense.
But this particular paper was one of the
first. I mean one of the attempts of
this class is to show you papers as they
evolved as opposed to like what's the
latest paper here. But yes, you can um
that might be another project idea of
like how do you evaluate the quality of
the reasoning chains if you don't want
to depend on just the final outcome as
the proxy [snorts] for correctness.
>> Yes. What if you problem
if you tell it fails as a parent even if
you tell the model the answer has been
not because it's just too complicated to
>> that's a great question. So uh
>> as as I told you in step four uh the
assumption is being made that the the
benchmark on which this is being done is
essentially uh where the problem is not
too difficult. It is within range or
some subset of the problems are within
range of the language model. Um and
typically you can uh
so so that that that is an assumption
that is made and then when you do
iteratively the model might get better
at certain point that it can start
handling these other problems.
So in the key like very should negative
sound this means that
you
so I'm just wondering is there
possibility that you you know from the
step two you know works well and if the
step three doesn't work and you just use
the step two positive step three
>> um so so
that's a great point let's come back to
that one so I think what I'll show you
by the end of the lecture is that
learning from negative examples has not
been nailed. Learning from positive
examples has been like if you have any
non-zero reward then you have an ability
to close the RL loop which is not happen
uh close the reinforcement learning loop
which is not happening yet in this
particular set of examples. So you do
need to be able to close the loop in
some way.
So if if you have negative examples
there are some papers that have tried to
learn from it but like that's not
something we'll cover today.
Yes,
>> I have a similar question like um how to
evaluate or verify quality of the
generated red nails on fail on this
fails after giving the hints like since
already know the answer but um it might
it might generate like a incorrect
reasoning that leads to
>> so that's a great problem to like uh so
you're saying that in step two it might
or in step three it might generate wrong
rationals is what you're saying then it
will learn wrong wrong wrong reasoning
from correct attempts yes that will be a
problem in this particular case they're
not they don't have any further uh
filtering on top of uh rationals
so there will be no way to hill climb in
that case
you can have humans look at the
reasoning chain
>> tedious
>> it could be tedious yes
okay So uh going through this in a
little bit more uh rigorous detail. So
you start with a prompt data set where
you have the questions the ration and
the answers. This uh prompt data set
will be small and uh compared to um the
amount of data that we want to train on.
For example, this is the multiple choice
questions um where do you put your
grapes just before checking out there's
a rationale and then the correct answer
is uh for example B which is grocery
cart. Now you have a training data set
which is quite large uh of examples that
have questions and answers. This would
be uh say if you have a benchmark you
might have a train subset of the
benchmark and test subset of the
benchmark and what vanilla star will do
is it will start with this rational data
set and training data set. So it will
first few short prompt the model with uh
the rationals in the rational data set
and then it will get the model to um
produce the rationals and the correct
output and then uh so this is on the
training data set. So now it's few short
prompting but it's supplying um pro
problems questions uh from the training
data set and it's checking if the
answers are correct by the language
model and it will collect these set of
uh rationals that it can use if they uh
and then it can fine-tune the language
model on these correct solutions. If you
have uh rationalization which is what
star uh does if the answer is incorrect
what you will do is you will add hint.
So you'll be saying okay here is the
correct answer and you will essentially
generate the rationale by looking at
this hint and then you you will use that
to to add to that data set of rationals
that led to the correct answer and then
you can fine-tune on top of that
language model and um so you basically
have these two sets of rationals that
then you can fine-tune on top of this
language model and you can do this
process iteratively. So you don't like
do it just once you fine-tune it. Now
the language model perhaps is able to
produce better reasoning chains. So now
you can again start with your training
data set and uh whatever was not correct
you can redo this process. So their
experiments were on a small model which
is an open- source uh of GPD3 a six
billion parameter model called GPDJ.
they had a pretty small warm-up uh and
then they kept a constant learning rate
and then they basically had certain
number of iterations of the outer loop
and then they increased uh the inner
loop the number of steps in the inner
loop on each step. So one of the
comments the paper makes is that they
want to start the they want to have a
slower start in the training time and
then they want to slowly increase uh the
number of u things that are happening in
the inner loop.
The data sets that they tried this on
was GSM 8K. U so GSM 8K is just uh math
problems that you have seen where you're
basically asking these are grade school
math problems. There are about 9K
samples. Then common sense QA. Common
sense QA is essentially uh problems that
would you would see on say related to
day-to-day stuff. So you will have these
multiple choice questions and then you
have these answers and there's
rationalization that looks like this.
and then arithmetic problems which
basically was some sort of an addition
problem on multi-digit addition.
So they generated the last one was uh
synthetic data where they randomly uh
like they generated some of these uh
things themselves.
So in terms of results uh some of the
results that stood out in this paper was
that just compared to say supervised
fine-tuning on say math benchmark they
could boost uh with this uh star
approach to 51.7 but they only used like
70 to 87% of the data in terms of like
uh so they had to throw out a whole
bunch of data that didn't did not have
correct solutions and um other challenge
is that it's not really true RL so if
you basically do multiple iterations of
this it starts to plateau after a while.
So uh I mean RL has its own set of
challenges but here it also starts to
plateau. So you have to really pay
attention to um how many iterations you
can do and there's some amount of
tweaking there that you have to do. Uh
the other interesting set of results
here were that um this was on common
sense reasoning. So so they actually
looked at um this was a question that
several folks asked here. They actually
tried to see the rationals for common
sense QA. They showed it to human
raiders and they asked human raiders to
say how likely they are to um prefer the
rationals from star versus like uh just
like uh otherwise. So star generated
rationals versus the few short rationals
in the the the rational data set. uh
they compared those and what they found
was that um generally the qualitative
analysis showed that their rationals
were pretty reasonable. Now common sense
QA as you remember is a natural language
um like it's tackling daily problems
here. So as a result of that um this
these seemed the rational seemed pretty
reasonable and then the other aspect
that they noticed was that uh star in
general requires like if you use direct
finetuning you you basically do get a
certain level of accuracy but star with
rationalization gets that accuracy but
it does not require that same like it
requires much less data compared to what
you would need for fine-tuning. So
rationalization helps you uh get to an
accuracy without um using like so 86% of
the data is used but you can basically
get to uh the deficit accuracy of 72.5%
compared to like using a lot of training
data. So this was a very small model. So
this was first science of life that was
shown for reasoning. U in terms of
mathematical reasoning this was an
interesting uh one on GSM8K. What they
found was that the use of
rationalization actually did not improve
performance. So like star by itself was
not helping in this particular case. Uh
so what you see is that you have uh GPDJ
like basically it improves of the
baselines but it's basically not helping
too much. Uh if you directly do
fine-tuning on good data then you can
actually improve it similarly. So one of
the reasons that is the case is the
number of calculation steps that were
used uh by the model themselves. if you
force the model to use chain of thought
versus you provide these rationalization
steps is actually pretty similar. So in
in some ways uh it was not helping if
the problem is too simple like the whole
notion of like getting the model to
reason if the model if the problem is
too simple was basically not helping. So
GSM8K for GPD40 was very much within
capability. So um similarly for GPDJ so
there was not much improvement here
relative to but it did show that direct
fine-tune versus star with
rationalization you still had some
gains.
Okay, so some takeaways here are that um
the whole notion of rationalization
conditions on the fact that you have an
answer and then you can essentially
figure out what rationals would would be
good and um the outputs without
rationalization are examples where the
model is already quite confident but
then uh the model is not yet but if you
can look at the answer then in certain
cases it might actually do a better job
producing the rationale and if you do
few short prompting you can basically
really help the model um in how it
should produce rational but um the style
of rational might actually influence the
model in certain ways. So you you do
have to like prompt engineering in this
particular case might might bias the
model in certain ways. So effectively
there are certain challenges. One
challenge is that um the rationalization
the quality has certain amount of
effects and the second bit is that if
you're few short prompting then you are
biased by how the rationals were
formatted in your uh few short prompts
and and that might affect what kind of
rationals the model will produce and
what you're training on. So overall I
think uh this kind of gives us a sense
of just that in the in the uh model
space if you basically bootstrap the
model to generate rationals you can get
high sample efficiency while not having
to get humans to generate these uh
reasoning chains and you can apply it to
many problems like you can apply it to
symbolic problems natural language
mathematical reasoning. The some of the
challenges that are there in this
overall techniques is that you don't
have a very good evaluation for ration
uh for most tasks because you basically
have to have a human evaluate them or
you need some sort of a process reward
model to evaluate them. Uh there might
be u true negatives and false positives.
So you are just filtering based on
correct answers. So you might have some
invalid steps in between which might
cause problems. Yes. So, so this
uh method is is useful for models,
right? Because if if you are if you are
if you want to fine a small language
model, you can just use a front model to
generate these training, right?
>> Oh, I don't know how to answer that
question.
>> So, so you don't have to rely on on on a
small model to generate you this uh new
additional data automatically. you can
just use a big model and it can train
stuff but I'm wondering that the the the
main benefit I mean you are actually
getting
>> getting training out from nothing
>> what is is is shows when you are
training something which is basically
the following
>> yes so the the goal for a lot of the
work that we're discussing is the
ability to I mean we're showing um the
solutions on small models but at the end
of the day what we wanted to want to be
able to do is take the model, take its
outputs and then use that to improve the
model. Um, you can always take a more
powerful model and use it outputs and
that's like distillation process. Um,
>> yeah, that's that's clear. I I mean the
the theory
attempt is clear but I mean when it
comes to practical application
>> yes
>> so so I will I will use this method when
I'm at opening I learn topic and I'm
training the next
one
parameter model and I need additional
data view what I have
>> that that's a fair point
[snorts] um or or you want to basically
uh improve the model on so instead
capabilities that they they actually
don't have they won't produce good model
outcomes on.
>> So so so what I mean is that so if if I
want to improve their performance over 7
billion
>> in practice then I I wouldn't use this
because I I get get high quality data
from
>> from this
is much easier.
>> We are not covering this relation but
that's fair point. Okay, thank you. Just
>> uh No, that's a fair point that you can
use one of the frontier models in distal
things, but this is more an attempt to
uh build it from scratch and for you
folks to understand what might that
take.
>> Yes,
>> question. I'm curious why this isn't
like full-fledged RL and also um whether
>> you're leading me to my next slide.
>> Okay, great. Oh, and also um I I'm also
curious uh so like when you would decide
to make the choice of to post train with
SFT versus RL and if there's any
different implications of how much data
or compute is needed.
>> Um hold that question until the end
[laughter]
but I'm covering that that's that's part
of the lecture.
Uh so just uh just to cover so in star
you basically were just using the
correct uh output which is like a proxy
for a verifier where like you already
know the answer. If you basically also
add a verifier in that whole loop then
that would be called var. So there was a
paper that basically had a generator and
a verifier training in a loop. And then
quietar was essentially adding an
internal thinking. So what it was doing
was essentially instead of having uh
reasoning steps be in the language
space, it was actually uh putting
reasoning steps in the latent space uh
with um MLPS. So why have them in
English when you can have them have the
model thinking internally?
So before I move further actually there
have been a lot of questions. I'll only
pick one of these questions but um
let's look at question two. What what is
uh what what bounds the performance of
star as an approach?
You can talk to someone for a minute and
then let's chat as a class.
>> Let's come on back as a class.
>> So what performance like what bounds the
performance of star as a technique that
multiplication of choice helps
I'm seeing no hands. You guys are
talking. All answers are welcome.
>> Yes.
>> I think this is kind of like a silly
like answer right here. We were thinking
like um there are some logical steps
that are kind of more complex than
others and you wouldn't expect star to
be able to make any logical leaps that
are not in its training data set, right?
like the rationalization
should all kind of be of the same level
as what it was dreamed of just this
allows it to get like you know more
rational rationalization data
>> okay okay so it will not make I I mean
it will basically not have a logical
leap into say new domain that will have
figured out new things is what you're
saying okay
any other takers
>> um absolutely
You care about new things. So you can't
really model to to do likeation
because like if the model is really bad
at like creating new
reasoning introduce wrong samples into
the training and like
>> say that loudly what you're saying.
>> Yeah. So we testing like this
performance is improved by the um by
model's capability to do reasoning
because
>> I see
>> yeah because
>> if the model can't reason even given the
hints that's also not going to work out
because the rationalization won't show
up at all. [snorts]
>> Yeah wrong samples
>> that that opens the question what leads
to reasoning
>> in the base model. I I think some some
answers make it inherently easier to um
rationalize than others. For example, if
the final answer is like 225, you
probably know that at some point.
There's like the multiplication of 15
and 15 or something similar to that. But
maybe some other numbers are not as
straightforward. And I also think that
um if there's a lot of a lot of problems
that you don't know the answer to and
that forces you to rationalize, then it
probably um you probably need more data
so that you can form more generalized
reasoning to backtrack.
>> Okay.
and that that is in the right direction.
Yes.
Okay. I think all of these answers are
fairly valid, but I think this is worth
keeping in the back of your mind as we
move into RL because a lot of the magic
in this particular domain is like what
can the base model do as we're building
on top of that.
Um so we'll we'll come back to that.
Okay. So the second paper that we'll
cover is deepseek math uh that will
focus on mathematical reasoning uh and
it will actually use a form of RL that
it proposed that has become quite
popular. So we already looked at this
graph earlier where we were basically
showing that in math domain if you do
train time scaling you can do much
better and okay um so what this slide is
showing is that if you look at the
performance so this is a earlier
benchmark than Amy it's actually a
simpler benchmark than Amy it's called
math uh benchmark and you're basically
looking at top at one accuracy so if you
look at the date of the benchmark you'll
see that as the model sizes increased
typically the accuracy on this benchmark
has gone up. But then suddenly when
Deepse seek math came out, a 7B model
was doing really well. Um and the main
leap that they made was that they were
able to do the reinforcement learning
part with this in the train time scaling
loop correctly. So we will see what led
to that uh innovation. So the first
thing that they got right was that
typically when you try to improve on
math and this was something that was
done on top of palm as a paper palm
model. Uh there was this paper paper
called minurva which improved palm model
on stem and what what they did was they
trained on a lot of science and math
data typically like archive data. What
deepseek did was it was like okay
actually training on archive papers is
not the trick. they actually trained on
common crawl web pages but they started
uh with a deep sea coder model. So they
said that if you start with a model that
has already been uh improved on code
reasoning that it will actually do
better and then they did a really good
job at
um curating from content from common
crawl pages on math and they found that
often archive papers in some ways don't
have adequate amount of uh math content
that would cover give us coverage. So,
open web math uh by curating that and
and mining it, they were able to
actually and and getting better coverage
across math domains, they were actually
able to get much larger yield in number
of tokens. And that was their first um
first exercise in like priming the model
before they take it to RL. So, this was
related to one of the comments that were
made that if the model is not strong in
a certain domain, you do have to improve
its capability in that domain. So, this
is that step. Um so they basically got
coverage across a lot of math domains
showed it a lot of high quality data in
math and they started from a code uh
code pre-trained model and so they
actually showed that archive training
was actually not really helping but code
to math significantly helped uh because
it allowed the model to reason better do
tool use better. This was actually the
first time that um uh this was shown
that like a model if you start from a
coding based model you could do better.
And then the other thing that they
showed was that um the curation of data
really helped in this particular case.
Now the second step that they did was
okay now that you have um this um like
you've trained the model on math using
supervised fine tuning what do you do
next? So they actually scale up their
RL. Now the typical RL algorithm that
has been used in RL for human feedback
even with verifiers is called PO. So you
have to keep your policy and your new
policy. So you basically this ends up
being a memory problem if you try to do
it on larger models. A 7B model is fine
but if you try to scale up uh RL you
have to keep multiple policy models and
then you also have to learn a critic
model and a reward model. So typically
in the RL loop you have an old policy a
new policy that you're learning. uh you
have a critic that's basically giving
feedback and then you have a reward
model that's assigning the rewards. So
keeping all four of the copies of models
starts to become challenging. So what
they did was they proposed a new
technique called GRPO where instead of
uh having a critic or a value function
estimate uh things they basically used
some sort of a generalized um advantage
estimation that I'll show you in the
next slide and then you only have three
copies of the model. So now the PO which
needed a lot more memory instead of that
GRPO essentially could use just a group
for the baseline and and the way that
works is that for each question you
sample a lot of the answers and then you
score them and you normalize the reward
of so this is the score that you gave
for each of the answers using the reward
model and then you normalize the reward
as reward minus mean of rewards divided
by standard deviation and then this
becomes your advantage basically. So
typically if you look at u the way DPO
works or all of those techniques works
you're basically going to compare the
rewards. So by doing a reward minus mean
of rewards divided by standard deviation
you're effectively providing a
comparative technique across rewards
and uh the why so the reason this made
sense was because reward models are
going to essentially be trained on
comparison anyway. So by providing the
grip context you can save memory and now
you can start scaling up RL and your
advantage function in this particular
case essentially. So I I didn't add the
full formula because I just wanted you
guys to have intuition. You could just
like take the reward subtract the
average reward and then divide that by
the spread of rewards and you can get an
estimate of the advantage. And on math
they were able to go from 46.8 to 51.7.
And this was actually the first open
source model at 7B scale that crossed
like 50% without having a critic. Um
this is a much earlier paper but then
this gives you a sense of the technique
that they used and further what they
showed was that if you look at different
variants of RL effectively what you are
changing is either the data source. So I
showed you how they curated their data
and then you're deciding how to compute
the gradients. The gradient depends on
gradient coefficient and uh the
probability
of the output given the question. So the
gradient coefficient computation changes
in different algorithms. So their
estimate of gradient coefficient was
coming from this um group estimator
group baseline uh which worked well for
a single singlestep problem where you're
just trying to get the answer. So if you
compare uh approaches like star where
you basically are just generating uh
things once and if you uh you get
correct one you basically get a reward
of one if it's correct and zero if it's
wrong or if you do online rejection
fine-tuning you are still uh generating
things online but you only get a reward
of one if it's correct and zero if it's
wrong. So you basically reject anything
that is incorrect. GRPO is generating uh
rewards online with the reward model,
but it's basically getting an advantage
function because you're doing multiple
samples and then you're giving them a
score and then the the advantage for
that score comes from this uh group
baseline by computing the mean and then
dividing it by the spread of rewards. So
um now you can ask me the question that
you were asking me earlier about the
difficulty of the problems.
>> Oh the difficulty of the problem that I
make regression on sensor questions.
>> Yes. Yes. So I'm curious um um if you
are updating the updating the model with
with fine tuning for difficult questions
you are essentially um updating all the
weights. So isn't that going to
potentially theoretically have any um
regression on similar questions or other
metrics?
>> So this is this is a table I wanted to
show you. So effectively um if you're
basically trying to close the loop, what
you're trying to figure out is how much
reward you're giving. So simple problems
effectively might uh equate to you're
going to get a reward of one anyways and
you're like never getting a reward of
zero. um and in with GRPO you're getting
some form of a distribution of rewards
um that I was showing here. So if you
don't have any distribution in rewards
then so effectively what you want is
some form of a distribution of rewards
across the set of problems you are
showing. If there is not a distribution
of rewards there's nothing for the model
to learn like if all the rewards are
zero or all the rewards are one then
basically the normalization doesn't
work. Does that make sense? Uh yeah yes
yes but
>> which we will solve in the next like the
like the the shortcoming of this
particular method we will solve in the
next paper
>> but but this reward is specific to um
like this one particular
feature that we're trying to train and
not like the basic overall holistic
benchmark that we trained for the
previous model before.
>> So I mean it is basically taking
problems and then computing answers
right. uh if across the model you
basically are showing problems that are
all very hard then the model has no
capacity to learn because it will
basically have no reward at any point
>> it needs some hill climbing signal right
>> like I'm not showing you a formula I'm
intuitively explaining it to you
>> yes
>> um yeah actually I just want to comment
on that piece quickly
>> I think my interpretation of actually
the solution to that is in the original
papers like bo that's why there's a kale
divergence term. So essentially it's
like it is a valid concern I think
because it's like if we're updating the
weights we could probably train really
far like model and maybe we can get
really good answer these benchmarks but
if we got the model to be really
optimized on all these like simple
benchmarks earlier straight away so I
think in addition to the normalized
rewards we also have some like
divergence and all
>> okay that's a fair interpretation uh
that you add divergence and then you
don't deviate from what it could already
solve. Okay.
>> Yeah, I was interpreting it more along
the lines of like how do you have good
distribution of problems so that the
model has the right hill climbing signal
but I think what you're saying is that
if the model could already solve
something then kill diversion solves
that part of the problem.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Question is like so if you were trying
to post post train so that it has like a
new feature do you really have to update
all the weights or
>> No, I don't think so. Right. And there
are some more recent works that have
shown there are some blog posts that
have been recently shown that um like
you can do with like lower updates and
so on.
So I I do think that either kale
divergence or some like subset of
features could solve that problem. I
think the
uh the reason this is interesting is
that you uh want um you want perhaps
that these kind of techniques allow you
to improve the model overall.
>> Yeah.
more questions.
>> I hope
you just have a
zero but at this point you have a score.
How do you come up with a score?
>> How do you come up with a clean score?
>> Oh, because you train a reward model,
right?
I mean, you can also have zeros and ones
there and then you can average things.
But uh
>> so zero line that they have thresh
>> no you so what I was showing you are
training a reward model that is
basically going to give you a score for
that feedback.
>> Yeah if you only use zero and one that
can be a proxy but then you can do some
averaging.
Okay.
So what this roughly tells you is that
if you do basically the online
reinforcement learning loop uh and your
sample from the current model that beats
um what we were doing earlier where
we're in star approach. Uh so overall
what they showed was that you can
improve the majority of the like if if
they had 32 tries it was improving the
majority at K but it was actually not
improving pass at K. So if if you were
basically looking and plotting pass at K
um say one is correct if you sample 32
times then that was not what was
improving in their paper. What was
improving was that majority of the
solutions become correct. Um that that's
what was improving in this particular
paper. So the model actually became more
consistent not fundamentally smarter was
what they showed.
Now we'll cover the last paper uh called
Dappo um which is basically going to fix
some of the problems uh with respect to
reasoning on harder problems. So if you
naively scale up uh gRPO and want to do
this on even a quen 32B model which is
very easily accessible and you would get
30% on amy benchmark and here I will
show you a lot of technical terms uh but
I will try to explain to you intuitively
some of the challenges in just doing
this on quen 32B ends up being like the
entropy of the model collapses the model
can become too confident the training
can become unstable and the response
length the model output length can
become uncontrollable like it can
explode uncontrollably but deepseek did
get 47% on Amy like the deepseek urban
paper did get 47% so DAPo as a published
piece of work tries to um make explicit
what what were the techniques in RL that
were not covered in say GRPO so some of
the techniques that uh they talk about
is the that in PO you have to do um so
you're basically trying to do some sort
of exploration in your standard PO
algorithm And um the standard PO
clipping uh treats the increasing and
the decreasing u on on on that very
similar. So basically if you have a low
probability token um it can only hill
climb so much and then the high
probability token has can also get
clipped. So the exploration can
collapse. Uh so basically the clipping
function in the the PO algorithm needs
to be asymmetric and that will allow
bigger increases. So that was the first
thing that Dappo found.
U in terms of graphs what that roughly
meant was that if you did clipping then
your accuracy was much better and if you
didn't uh do if you could allow clipping
higher if you could allow asymmetric
clipping the purple plot shows you that
you could achieve much higher accuracy
and your entropy on the right side
stayed more stable and did not collapse
while if you uh did have uh did I invert
that? So, so this is higher accuracy and
then the entropy is looking nicer and
then if you did not do asymmetric
clipping then your entropy has
collapsed. So you entropy is a proxy for
how much exploration is possible in the
model.
A second uh very interesting technique
which actually relates to what we were
talking about earlier was something
called as dynamic sampling. So what I
showed you for uh GRPO was that okay you
go and sample 64 solutions and then you
come up with a distribution on them and
then then you take a group baseline.
What uh Dapo said was okay well um how
about we oversample how about we don't
just use 64 samples how about we
oversample and then what we want is that
we will filter out things that have
zeros and zero reward and one reward so
that what we want is basically a nice
distribution so that uh most of the
solutions uh have some sort of a signal.
So they filter out all correct and all
wrong groups and they keep only some
subset uh between 0 and 64. So they
they're basically doing dynamic sampling
because they don't want to waste their
gradient. Your advantage should not be
zero. Like if you're if you're basically
your rewards are all correct or all
wrong then those groups are filtered out
and you essentially want to keep only
those groups that have um some signal.
So this maintains an effective batch
size because in RL if you have effective
batch size for propagating the gradients
because you're not computing gradients
from all correct and all wrong. Anyways
questions
>> group
question. Yes. So you have a batch of uh
questions when you are training and then
you're uh filtering out questions.
Yeah. Um, it seems 64 samples is quite
small. I I'm wondering if it's because
like there's very limited amount of Amy
questions out there and like whether
that was enough.
>> So this was a this is more an exemplar
here. You can choose how many samples
you pick but at the end of the day uh
this this is mostly to showcase what was
possible from their paper. So Amy yeah
yeah yeah this will be benchmark
specific and the difficulty of the
benchmark and the [snorts] capability of
the base model
and I think the the third bit that is
worth noting is that the reasoning
chains um have certain amount of um
length that matters. So if you are
basically doing a sample level loss uh
sample level means that for each
question answer pair that that sequence
you're computing a loss then each answer
is basically counted globally. So um in
certain cases if you have a very long
garbage answer in the model output then
that basically gets same weight as a
short good answer. So they effectively
suggest that you should have some sort
of a effectively length penalty but
which should put uh better like they
want a shape uh based on the length. So
they put a token based low loss as
opposed to putting a sample level loss
and that they gave them some gain. And
in particular what they were controlling
for is both the entropy and the mean
response length. So effectively if they
didn't have a token level loss they were
noticing that the entropy was growing
and the response length was also uh not
looking like it was control um it was
growing uncontrollably. So they wanted
to shape that better by putting some
form of a penalty there.
So they put um token level loss for
that. And then finally um there are
certain cases in which um the model
encounters a hard problem. So it
basically gets truncated at the end
because um it was thinking it was
basically producing model outputs and
and these truncated uh reasoning chains
can generate a lot of noise. So they
basically put a gradual penalty in and
in in the tokens to to deal with that
and that allowed the training to become
stable instead of adding noise. So
effectively uh the generation entropy
instead of uh becoming unstable uh once
the model was learning to generate like
really like the model as it progresses
starts to um generate longer and longer
reasoning chains and that can that can
get truncated and that can cause
problems. So there are a couple of
different ways in which different papers
have tried to tackle this. one is that
either they increase the context length
over RL loop um to handle that in this
particular case they are basically
putting this uh penalty function so that
they can handle this this part.
So overall what this showed was that
when you started with GRPO on this AMA
benchmark if you put overong filtering
you went from 30 to 36 on the quen 32B
model. If you did asymmetric clipping,
you could go to 38. With soft overong
punishment, you could go to 41. And then
with token level loss, you go to 42. And
then if you do dynamic sampling, where
you're basically doing a better
distribution of rewards um across the
batch, you have a better signal
propagation. You basically got to 50,
which was even better than what DeepS R1
uh distilled down to Quen 32B had done.
So they could actually hill climb on the
quen 32B themselves and and get to a
pretty strong score here.
So some of the learnings from this paper
was that the loss function by itself was
not a reasonable enough proxy when
you're learning in RL. You have to look
at the response length. You have to look
at the entropy and keep it so that it's
not too low but it's not too high
either. And then uh the percentage of
samples that have uh a full accuracy of
one tells you how much you need to
sample. So that's all of all three are
important principles in uh learning in
RL and some of the challenges that you
might have to look out for is that if
your response length in the model
outputs is exploding then you have to
control the loss there. You have to
control the entropy and then if you're
not seeing improvement after um certain
number of steps then your reward model
actually might be saturated.
Uh so effectively what this is saying is
that the
the optimization in the RL loop is
harder. So if I were to answer the
question that was brought up earlier of
like SFT versus RL, RL does provide you
uh in the domains where there you do
have a strong reward signal. It does
provide you the ability to hill climb
with fewer number of examples but it
does take a lot of work to like get it
right. Well, supervised fine-tuning
oftentimes if you do have access to a
lot of high quality data is faster way
to just improve the model performance in
certain cases, but it doesn't bring
reasoning trace reasoning capabilities
or boost them in in certain ways.
So if you want to compare the the three
different techniques uh that we uh
talked about today. Um so if you
basically only had a few different
examples like 100 examples with
reasoning and you are effectively just
like playing around uh with a model star
is a pretty good and you don't have RL
infrastructure. Star is a pretty good
way for you to like start getting the
model to reason. um and and simple
reasoning tasks like GSM8K actually will
see reasonable amount of improvement
there. Maybe not phenomenal, but like
you're still staying within what the
model was capable of. If you go to
Deepseek Math um and you use GRPO, you
do need a good enough base model plus
like uh you do need to u prime the model
with with good instruction data. But now
um you have a reasonably strong
algorithm that that can work even if you
don't have enough memory. if you have a
limited number of GPUs and then for
standard math reasoning tasks this was
well proven
and then if you uh and you need do kind
of uh techniques when your reasoning
chains will end up being longer which
typically correlates with harder
problems so if your reasoning chains are
going to be uh much longer you need
state-of-the-art performance then you do
need to control all of these variables
in your RL algorithm and infrastructure
but for compet competition level
problems like Amy and IMO this is very
useful
So what is it that we expect to improve?
All three techniques will improve in
general the majority at K performance on
the y-axis as you put more compute. Um
the answer formatting and generally will
improve as you apply these techniques
and uh in general the model will be more
coherent over multiple steps but none of
these will yet improve the fundamental
capability or just teach the model to
solve no new problems or generalize a
lot out of domain. So there is some set
of questions that are being asked at
this point in time. What would it take
for the the last part to start
improving?
>> Yes.
part is because I wonder whe
the part like all brand or all because
that's if you
>> Mhm. That's like uh the only way you
like on the page and you improve on so
because we all
>> I see
>> I'm just a
>> uh that's not the reason I think the
more fundamental question is that to
improve pass at K you're basically
improving the fundamental capability of
the model to solve new problems right So
you want to see the model uh show
capabilities in certain ways. So
typically the fundamental capability
scaling comes from uh the fundamental
capability step jumps have typically
been seen by either some sort of a
breakthrough or by scaling in some
dimension.
>> Okay. So if you actually see that this
thing for a set of the problems always
give the answer then it's possible that
I'm not sure whe is good to do so but
you can answer the question to some
other models you're going to get the
answer and you can go back to
>> let's take that one offline
>> um okay so one of the thing that I keep
highlighting um is something to keep in
mind is that a lot the RL loop or even
the star method like the quality of
rational all of that depends on the
ability of the model to reason or there
there needing to be some sort of a
verifier or a reward model and the
reward models if the model is too
capable then the reward rewards will get
hacked or and if the reward model
doesn't have enough signal then you're
basically not able to hill climb the
loop. So it is a harder optimization
problem in that respective. Um we looked
at last um last lecture uh or last
Friday we looked at the autonomous
coding applications where you do have
access to verifiable rewards because you
have like in math and code you have the
final correct answer then you can also
give execution feedback which was the
RLEF paper we looked at and then you
also have unit test execution. Um
similarly in other there are some
domains in which you have this kind of
verification available. So it's easy for
you to uh hill climb but then how many
such places do you have this signal
available? These questions will continue
to come up. So um like what verification
signals are good enough and then there's
can you use a ensemble of verifiers
instead of like one single verifier to
make up for the gaps of what a single
verifier will provide signal on. So all
of these questions are extremely
important.
So in terms of if you were to look at
open problems uh in this domain so I
think this is still an active train time
scaling is an active area of research uh
I already highlighted this there's a
fundamental question of like why only
majority at K increases why why does
pass at K doesn't increase a second
question is that um we do see in the
reasoning chains um things like
backtracking or the model is able to
like self-evaluate self-correct we did
show those examples early on, but are
those behaviors real? Like these
reasoning behaviors, are they emerging
or were they already like present and
they're basically statistically becoming
more prevalent? And then a third bit
right now is that we don't really have
very good techniques to learn from
failures. There have been a few papers
that have tried to uh learn from
failures in useful ways, but currently a
lot of the techniques just filter them
out. Some uh some promising directions
that people continue to explore in this
is uh along the data dimension of like
how do you generate better data to train
the model along the algorithm dimensions
of like how do you get the reinforcement
learning to be robust to noise in the
reward models what kind of rewards
should we use and then can you combine
some of the rationalization techniques
that we did with um in star with say the
techniques that we did in DAPo. So all
of those are u very interesting
directions that that you could look into
for your projects.
And with that we have a few minutes
left. Um but let's have questions.
>> Um for like the new like being like out
of the box like models it
are training. How much do you think
they're still relying on just like just
common call like next to prediction like
just just like blank like like raw text
data right like that they take from like
the internet right or anywhere
rather than like instruction tuning data
that like they generate like using
reasoning techniques and techniques that
we learn today like what do you think is
that fraction
>> I think so I think the like I don't
think that's published for entropic but
I think rock was more public. So
typically the percentage of um
reinforcement learning uh versus uh
pre-training has been closer to I think
last year it was closer to say 99% 1%
and then it's grown to perhaps like 5%
or something like that but Grock claimed
that Grock 4 claimed that it did 50% RL
but it actually did not quite improve 50
like 50% RL should give a big jump but
you're [snorts] bottlenecked by a lot of
the things that I'm showing you here of
like your your rewards are not strong
enough or there's noise in rewards. All
of those things are going to be
bottlenecks. So there's still a lot of
open problems in this domain. Yeah.
Uh let's see if there are more questions
across the board or is this lecture too
complex for people to ask questions
too complex? Okay.
Happy to answer questions after
>> more questions across the class. No,
>> I will like for example.
>> Mhm. Is this something like if you
if the model perform okay in this
calculus and you help it to perform
better by RL
the model never see always fail in
regardless how well they can never
fundamental reason like K is like
fundamentally you think you need
>> Mhm. But like you better
>> exactly.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So
maybe that's something like there's more
to learn because [clears throat] it's
getting better at something you already
can do.
>> Yeah. You mean it's basically able to
explore better in the design space of
what it knows and by exploration and
search it's able to arrive at the
solution.
There was a question here which I didn't
let you ask.
>> All right. Yeah. I I was curious for um
especially on the directions of data. Um
so uh for very unique data set like Amy
or USML where the number of data sets is
very limited. Um how can we uh ensure
that we have enough signals for
verifiable rewards? Um I mean like
there's not enough data but we need a
lot of signals. So how can you kind of
like make sure that you have enough
training and verification without
accidentally leaking data?
>> So uh I mean RL is more data efficient.
So you do not need that much data to
begin with. So I mean like that's why I
was presenting these papers you do see
that u certain number of like enough
examples is going to enough to help
climb. Uh the verification signals are
more a function of like having good set
of verifiers. So I think I thought you
already covered the ensemble verifier
paper, right? Like we were you already
covered that. So it's it's not just a
matter of having a single verifier, you
can have multiple verifiers.
>> I see. So when there's not enough data,
we can just make up for that with many
more verifiers.
>> So I think you solve the data problem
separately, but like I don't think the
not enough data is the right
abstraction. I think it's do you have
enough data to hill climb on is the
right abstraction, right?
like where you don't end up filtering
out if you were doing dynamic sampling
for example.
>> Okay, with that we'll close the class
and I'm still around. Thanks everyone.